<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A messenger sent to remove some mistakes; or A desirous instrument for the promoting of truth, unity, peace and love in the church of Christ. By way of answer to a book, untruly and improperly intitled, A vindication of that righteous principle of the doctrine of Christ called laying on of hands upon baptized believers. / By Thomas Morris, a servant of Jesus Christ. Also Robert Everards Three questions propounded to Benjamin Morley about his practice of laying on of hands, with his answer, and R. E. reply.</title>
            <author>Morris, Thomas, Baptist.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2811</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3541</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E838_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E838_23*</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207456</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 127:E838[23] or 127:E838[23*])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A messenger sent to remove some mistakes; or A desirous instrument for the promoting of truth, unity, peace and love in the church of Christ. By way of answer to a book, untruly and improperly intitled, A vindication of that righteous principle of the doctrine of Christ called laying on of hands upon baptized believers. / By Thomas Morris, a servant of Jesus Christ. Also Robert Everards Three questions propounded to Benjamin Morley about his practice of laying on of hands, with his answer, and R. E. reply.</title>
                  <author>Morris, Thomas, Baptist.</author>
                  <author>Everard, Robert, fl. 1664. Robert Everards Three questions propounded to Benjamin Morley.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42; 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.E. and are to be sold by Richard Moon, at the seven Stars neer the North Door of Pauls Church.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Robert Everards Three questions (Wing E3541).. has a caption title, separate pagination and register.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Morley, Benjamin. A vindication of that righteous principle of the doctrine of Christ called laying on of hands upon baptized believers.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 19".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Morley, Benjamin. --  Vindication of that righteous principle of the doctrine of Christ called laying on of hands upon baptized believers.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MESSENGER SENT To remove ſome miſtakes; OR A DESIROUS INSTRUMENT For the promoting of TRUTH, UNITY, PEACE and LOVE in the CHURCH of CHRIST.</p>
            <p>By way of Anſwer to a Book, untruly and improperly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, A vindication of that righteous principle of the Doctrine of Chriſt called laying on of hands upon Baptized believers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> THOMAS MORRIS, <hi>a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Robert Everards</hi> three Queſtions propounded to <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin Morley</hi> about his practice of laying on of hands, with his Anſwer, and <hi>R. E.</hi> Reply.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God; a workman that need not to be aſhamed, rightly dividing the word of truth
<bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 2.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>To the Law, and to the teſtimony: if they ſpeak not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. E.</hi> and are to be Sold by <hi>Richard Moon,</hi> at the ſeven Stars neer the North Door of <hi>Pauls</hi> Church. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168156:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168156:2"/>
            <head>To all that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ear Brother, and Brethren, I, taking notice of the deſign of Anti-Chriſt, whoſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is to ſee the Church of Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and his honour flouriſh, it being the decay of his worldly honour and wicked Government, and ſo he hath as from the very root of envy againſt the honour of Jeſus Chriſt, and the good of his Church, his, <hi>viz.</hi> Anti-Chriſts honour, and intereſt being concerned in his deſign, which moves him to indeavour the ruin of Chriſts honour, and of his people in that, he hath in theſe laſt days indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to confound Chriſts Church, and the way his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple walk in, by uſing Inſtruments to perſwade them to ſhift obedience to Gods Ordinances, eſpecially in point of Baptiſm, and breaking of Bread, pretending as if he hath brought in a new diſpenſation by way of Revelation and immediate inſpiration, conſiſting of the power of Godlineſs without the form; ſometimes appearing like an Angel of light in point of opinion, and ſometimes like a civil honeſt man for matter of converſation, thinking the Church of Chriſt could not have eſpied his painted blaſphemy in point of opinion, nor his diſſembling hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie in uſing civil honeſty as a cloak for his Knavery;
<pb facs="tcp:168156:3"/>ſo that under pretence of bringing men over to ſerve Chriſt in a higher diſpenſation, as he calls it, he might bring them to ſerve himſelf in a blaſphemous way, giving God the lye, in ſaying he hath not commanded the Saints now to be Baptized in water, nor to hold viſible Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the Supper, or breaking of Bread; and thus he indeavours to divide the Church of Chriſt by this means: but when he could not prevail utterly to confound the Church this way, Chriſt having ſome ſtout Souldiers, who as inſtruments under God did withſtand him, he now attempts utterly to ruin the Church of Chriſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way; for finding many in the Church, whom he cannot by his former deſign deceive, they were ſo zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for obedience to Gods Ordinances, he now lays his bait where he thinks it is moſt likely to catch, <hi>viz.</hi> in actions relating to Ordinances, and ſo with ſomething like truth, which is not truth, but an error ſo neatly dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with truths habit, that few are able to look through truths habit, ſo as to ſee the ugly ſhape of errour that barks under it: he ſtrikes at the very being of the Church; and therefore ſeeing Gods honour and the Churches Peace and well being is ſo much concerned in it, I deſire all my dear Brethren and Friends, as they with me tender Gods honour and the Churches well being, Impartially to read and deliberately to conſider this following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, the which if you do, though Anti-Chriſt hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with ſome, who have a great influence upon the Churches to be Inſtrumental for the promoting of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, though I verily believe they know it not, but as ſome zealous Presbyters do, when they ſprinkle Infants think they do God good ſervice, you ſhall ſee this error ſtript of truths habit, and laid open in its own colours; and whereas Brother <hi>Morly</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Reader ſeems
<pb facs="tcp:168156:3"/>to be the more confident in his way, becauſe the Biſhops kept the name of Gods Ordinances, of which, ſaith he, laying on of hands was one; but I muſt tell him and you, that for my part I dare not receive neither the name nor nature of Baptiſm, nor laying on of hands, as from what the Biſhops ſaid or did, no further then they ſaid and did according to the rule of Scripture; and ſo if your practice had been ſuch a one, as had been taught by way of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and injoyned by way of Command from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it had been well; but your practiſe of laying on of hands being ſuch a one as is neither taught by way of Doctrine, nor injoyned by way of Command, is of the more ſad and dangerous conſequence, as ſad experience hath proved; ſo hoping you will take the Counſel of the Spirit of God by the Apoſtle; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. <hi>viz. To examin your ſelves whether you be right in the Faith or not,</hi> I ſhall refer you to the following diſcourſe for further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and reſt and remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Fellow Servant in the Faith and Fellowſhip of the Goſpel,</hi> THOMAS MORI<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168156:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough upon the reading of this following Treatiſe, thou mayſt diſcover two friends contending one againſt another, yet take heed that thou doeſt not ſtumble and fall; for though an unhappy difference is now fallen out in the Church of Chriſt, yet it is no new thing, for in the Apoſtles time <hi>Acts 17.2.7.10.</hi> there was great contention amongſt the Brethren, whether or no Circumciſion was of neceſſity to ſalvation; therefore think it not ſtrange that Brethren ſhould differ in ſome things; for if thou doſt ſtumble, thou mayſt fall and periſh, when the parties differing may be reconciled and live for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; but if it ſhould ſo unhappily fall out, that this one thing ſhould cauſe us to break our viſible Communion, yet know, that I hope we have all of us better learned Chriſt, than to turn back again to the beggarly rudiments of the National Church of <hi>England;</hi> ſo hoping thou wilt be wiſe for Gods glory and thine own good, I ſhall leave thee to him, who is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance, <hi>2 Pet. 3.9.</hi> and would have all men ſaved <hi>1 Tim. 2.4.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>And ſhall ſtill remain a well wiſher to thy Soul.</hi> THOMAS MORRIS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168156:4"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO Mr. MORLEYES Firſt Chapter.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi>By</hi> THOMAS MORRIS.</byline>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Thomas.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He difference between you and I, as in relation to thoſe two ſorts of laying on of hands, you treated on in your firſt Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Officers and Sick, is ſo little, that I ſhall at preſent ſay nothing to them, onely methinks you are overſeen in the beginning of this Chapter, in ſaying you would treat of thoſe lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on of hands, which you find in Scripture, and not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with any other: and yet there in your naming of them you have left out two, <hi>viz.</hi> that of the Saints patient ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering perſecution from the hands of wicked men, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.12 and ſecondly, that laying on of hands, ſubjected too in order to the receiving of the gift of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts,</hi> 8. and alſo becauſe you name one which the Scripture ſpeaks not of in that way which you preach and practice it; and ſo much as to your firſt Chapter. In anſwer to your ſecond Chapter.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing I take notice of in your ſecond Chapter, (wherein is onely indeavoured the maintaining of ſuch a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168156:5"/>laying on of hands, as you preach and practice) Ben. <hi>is this;</hi> (you ſay) <hi>for as much as all the doubt lies, concerning bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed Believers, ſubjecting themſelves to a laying on of hands, as an Ordinance of Chriſt, which they ought now to be ſound in the practice of:</hi> and as your ſpeaking to this particular, you ſay you deſire to uſe plainneſſe of ſpeech, becauſe as you ſay, you are aſſured that the Apoſtle ſpeaks truth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.19. when he ſaith he had rather ſpeak five words to the underſtanding, then ten thouſand in an unknown tongue, and ſo you lay down this which you call a plain po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>viz.</hi> that Baptized Believers, ought to have hands laid on them as Baptized Believers. <hi>Thom.</hi> Firſt I ſtrange you ſhould pretend to uſe ſo much plainneſs, and yet lay down ſo dark a Poſition; for had I not heard you declare your ſelf by words of mouth, I could hardly have underſtood from your Poſition, whether you do affirm it to be the duty of all Baptized Believers, or not, nor what you had meant by the terms, as, Baptized Believers: but having heard you ſay that you now hold it not to be the duty of all Baptized Believers, but onely ſuch as have faith in it, and ſeeing you have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly Preached it to be the duty of all baptized Believers, I wonder you ſhould now confine it to ſome, unleſſe it be becauſe you cannot prove the tearm all: but you had as good have ſaid ſtill as you ſaid at firſt: for when (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your practice) I grant it a duty for ſome believers; I will grant it a duty for all, for if you could but prove it a duty for ſome believers for theſe ends, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, to be put into a furth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> capacity to go on to perfection: ſecondly, to compleat their ſubjection: thirdly, to compleat the order of their ſubjection; and fourthly, to demonſtrate love to Jeſus Chriſt, for which ends, you ſay, you do it: it muſt needs be the duty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all: for it behoves all to be in a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and to perfect their ſubjection, and the order of it, and to demonſtrate love to Jeſus Chriſt, as well as ſome;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168156:5"/>but I muſt tell you, that faith is not that Root from whence duty ſprings or receives its being; for if it were ſo, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty received its being from faith, then whatſoever God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, if we do not believe it, it is not duty, and ſo no blame for, nor danger in neglect; and on the other hand if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Infant Baptiſme, or any thing elſe, it would become duty, if duty received its being from believing; but duty ſprings from another root, and receives its being from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> from command; for as command receives its being from God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.49.50. ſo duty receives its beginning from command, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Fear God and keep his Commandements, for this is the whole duty of man,</hi> and performance of duty receives its being from the creature, inabled thereunto by the Creator, as appears, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.2 4. the doing of our duty in point of believing, doth not make another thing duty: onely Faith proceeding, renders the following action ſeaſonably done; ſo by this time I hope you ſee your miſtake, in ſaying it is not their duty, except they have faith in it, and how little it will avail you for the proof of your practice. Now to the proof you bring to prove your dark Poſition. <hi>Ben.</hi> You ſay you will give us clear Scripture for the confirmation thereof, you will give us evident reaſons; and ſubſtantial pure Scripture conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; in the firſt place you bid us caſt our eyes upon that you call a full Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. from the 17. where we ſhall ſee <hi>Philip</hi> Preaching the things concerning the Kingdome of God, and the name of Jeſus; and how they that believed were baptized both men and women, and how if we pleaſe to read on, we ſhall find that the principal motives, which did induce the brethren for to ſend <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> for to lay hands on them, were, firſt, becauſe they were Believers: and ſecondly, becauſe they were baptized Believers; and that theſe were the principal motives, you ſay doth plainly appear, from the 14. <hi>verſe.</hi> The term now you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168156:6"/>ſay carries the very life &amp; ſtrength of the former poſitions as much as if the holy Ghoſt ſhould ſay, Now is a time to ſend ſome faithfull brethren to <hi>Samaria,</hi> for now they are Believers, now they are baptized, now it is requiſite they ſhould ſubject to laying on of hands; and indeed the very next thing which was done on their parts was, ſubjection to this truth; we do not find any thing in that interval but prayer, and that was on <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Johns</hi> part, and not on theirs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, that the <hi>Samaritans</hi> were baptized Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, it is a truth, and that the conſideration of their having received the word of God, did move the brethren to ſend <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to them, it is true; but that to lay hands on them, was the ſpeciall thing they aimed at, cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but rather that which they did in ſpecial aim at, was that they might inſtrumentally poſſeſſe the Samaritans of the gift of the holy Ghoſt, for underſtanding that he was not fallen upon any of them: the firſt thing they did, they prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them that they might receive the holy Ghoſt, and when they had laid their hands on them, they did receive the holy Ghoſt. From whence it appears, that the holy Ghoſt was the ſpeciall mercy they deſired to poſſeſs them with, and prayer and laying on of hands were but the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental means they uſed for the attaining of it; and as for the tearm <hi>now,</hi> it can put neither life nor ſtrength to your poſition, becauſe it is no command, the tearm <hi>now</hi> onely notes out the time of their hearing the news, which was the ſeaſon in the which they ſent <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>John,</hi> as appears from theſe tearms: <hi>now when they heard they ſent:</hi> but that the term, now, notes or lays out any injunction upon the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans to come under laying on of hands, in any ſence it is as far from proving, as it is from proving Infants Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, which is far enough, and therefore you were too for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to call it truth, before you had brought better grounds to prove it.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:168156:6"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Secondly, ſay you to the next part of the <hi>Poſition</hi> that it is to be adminiſtred and ſubjected to next in order un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Baptiſme, is very plaine; it was when they had believed <hi>Philip</hi>'s preaching the things concerning the Kingdome of God, and the name of Jeſus, they were baptized, both men and women; from whence I argue my firſt Argument: If they had not impoſition of hands as Church Officers, nor as ſick parties, then they had it as Baptized Believers, but the former is true, therefore the latter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer. In theſe words, you ſay you will prove the next part of your <hi>Poſition, viz.</hi> that it is to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred and ſubjected next in order unto Baptiſme; and yet no part of your <hi>Poſition</hi> ſpeaks any ſuch thing: but whether it was done next in order unto Baptiſme, or not, it will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make for you, nor againſt me, ſeeing we differ not much about that: and though you ſay it's being done next to Baptiſme, leads you to this Argument: yet your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument doth not ſay one word that they had it next to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: but ſayes they had it as Baptized Believers: but for anſwer to that more anon: and whereas you render ſome Reaſons, why they had it not, as Church Officers, nor as ſick parties, in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. I grant you they had it not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>The next Scripture which you ſay, will plainly prove your <hi>Poſition,</hi> is in <hi>Acts</hi> 19.12, 5.6. that ſay you which may be gathered from this Text, is, Firſt, that thoſe people were Believers. Secondly, that they were Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Believers. Thirdly, that they had laying on of hands after Baptiſme, which ſay you leads you to this ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: Thoſe who have laying on of hands next in order unto Baptiſme, they have laying on of hands as Baptized Believers: but thoſe had laying on of hands next in order to Baptiſme: therefore they had laying on of hands as baptized Believers, the latter part of the <hi>Major Propoſition</hi> may ſeem ſomewhat doubtfull: namely, although they had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168156:7"/>laying on of hands next in order unto Baptiſme: yet ſome may queſtion whether they had it impoſed as baptized Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers: to which I doe argue further—3. Argument, If they had not laying on of hands, as unbaptized perſons, then they had laying on of hands as baptized perſons: but then they had not laying on of hands as unbaptized per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, for the Text ſaith, <hi>they believed and were baptized,</hi> and then they had hands laid on them: ſo that the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion followes, that they had laying on of hands as baptized perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer in ſpeaking to this your third Argument, I ſhall alſo anſwer to your two Former: for you concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that a doubt might ariſe from a latter part of the major <hi>Propoſition</hi> in your 2. Argument: to remove that doubt, you did lay downe this third Argument, in the which you tell us what you mean by termes, as baptized Believer, in your two former Arguments, as alſo in your <hi>Poſition:</hi> that is as much as to ſay, thoſe who when they have hands laid on them are not unbaptized, but baptized: Receive it as baptiſed Believers, which muſt needs be true: for unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed perſons cannot have hands laid on them as baptiſed perſons: yet this avails you nothing; for thoſe baptiſed Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers who ſuffer Perſecution from the hands of wicked men, have it as baptiſed Believers, becauſe they are ſuch; and ſo thoſe in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. who received laying on of hands in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their receiving the Holy Ghoſt, through which as an inſtrumentall means the Holy Ghoſt was given, received it as baptized Believers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>And now to the laſt Clauſe in the <hi>Poſition,</hi> That baptized Believers are to ſubject to the adminiſtration of it as baptized Believers this is very clear: as in both theſe Scriptures is made manifeſt. The <hi>Samaritans</hi> did not reſiſt <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> nor thoſe certaine Diſciples at <hi>Epheſus, Paul;</hi> which is a very clear demonſtration, that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168156:7"/>of the neceſſity of it: Had it not been a truth, but then to yeeld ſubjection to, I am perſwaded they would have adviſed the Apoſtles to have deſiſted from that work, and that becauſe they well knew, that whatſoever was not of Faith, was ſin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, that they were to ſubject to the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it, as baptiſed Believers, it's granted: becauſe baptiſed Believers: if they ſubject at all, can doe no other but ſubject as baptiſed Believers, which agrees with the ſenſe of your third Argument: yet this makes nothing for it upon that account you practiſe it: And whereas in effect, you ſay they being convinced of the neceſſity of it, moved them to ſubject; I think they were as much convinced of the neceſſity of it as the Apoſtles were, when Chriſt waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their feet, who knew not what he intended till after he had done it, as appears, <hi>Iohn</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 5. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 12, 13, 14, 15. And although Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſaith, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. were very Idiots if they ſubjected to that they knew no command for; he might as well have ſaid, the Diſciples of Chriſt were very Idiots, becauſe they let their Maſter waſh their feet, before they knew what he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, as is clear from <hi>Iohn</hi> 13.5.12, 13, 14, 15. and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I thinke that geſture of laying on of hands in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. was uſed only as Liberty, and not as Duty, for theſe two Reaſons: Firſt, becauſe there is nothing revealed, that there was any command for that geſture. Secondly, becauſe if it had been duty, it muſt be alwayes uſed as an inſtrument for the receiving the Holy Ghoſt; or elſe when the Holy Ghoſt was given, and no hands laid on before, duty muſt needs be neglected; but we read in the <hi>Acts,</hi> of five times the Holy Ghoſt was given; and yet but two times hands laid on; it was given in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. the 4, 8, the 10. and the 19. and onely in the 8. and 19. hands laid on; which makes it appear, it was uſed as a Liberty, and not as Duty, and ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168156:8"/>alſo to us, onely command will open a door for duty; and ſuch examples as we can, and it is convenient we ſhould imitate, will open a door for Liberty. But ſome will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and ſay, examples doe bind, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>ſo walke as you have us for an example.</hi> Anſwer, if you looke upon the Fore-part of theſe words, you ſhall ſee a command in theſe two termes; <hi>ſo walke,</hi> the following words being doctrinall: but I believe every rationall man will grant that theſe words muſt be taken reſtrictively only to follow them in ſuch things as we can, and it is conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent we ſhould imitate them; for if we ſhould take it gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, <hi>viz.</hi> to follow them in all things they have left exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, then we muſt caſt out Devils, heale the ſick, cleanſe the Lepers, circumciſe, with many other things; which either we cannot, or elſe it is not convenient we ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them in: But then ſay you,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Well my friends, was it then a truth, and was it never repealed. I mean laying on of hands upon baptized Believers, we then reaſon further.</p>
               <p>4th <hi>Argument,</hi> That which was once in being a truth, and never yet repealed, remains to this day in truth, in being; but laying on of hands upon baptized Believers, was once a truth in being, and never yet repealed, therefore: that it is not repealed, I thus prove.</p>
               <p>5th <hi>Argument,</hi> That which was once in force, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture making no mention of its repeal, that is not repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; but the practiſe was once in force, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes no mention of its repeal. <hi>Ergo,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, according to the ſenſe of your third <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,</hi> I grant you, it was a truth in being, <hi>viz.</hi> that thoſe which are not unbaptized when hands are laid on them: but baptized, have it as baptized ones, and not as unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized ones, though the end may be Inſtrumental to be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the Holy Ghoſt, as <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. or to be inſtated into office, as <hi>Acts</hi> the 6.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:168156:8"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap> the parts of your Poſition, is in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. From whence you infer, that thoſe baptized Believers of the <hi>Hebr.</hi> had once ſubjected to laying on of hands, which you ſay ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the termes, Leave, and not laying again; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle you ſay, doth allude to the builder of a houſe, who having laid his Foundation, is to build higher till he have perfected his work; and that the Apoſtle would have the Believer, who hath begun to doe his duty, to God, to goe on to perfect it; you tell us further, that in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. a laying on of hands is ſpoken of, and give us three Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why it was not in the caſe of Church Officers, nor of the ſick; and you ſay not of Perſecution, and then you conclude, That becauſe it is not meant of the three former accounts, though you ſhew no grounds againſt that of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, then it muſt needs be upon that other, <hi>viz.</hi> as bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Believers, and how that this Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. is a ſtronger piece of armour, than your Antagoniſts doe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for the bearing of the blame of mens imaginations, and to keep the body of your diſcourſe from being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, that theſe <hi>Hebrewes</hi> were baptized Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and that they had ſubjected to laying on of hands, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſenſe of your three Arguments, though not according to the manner of your practiſe, and that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth allude to the builder of a houſe, and that the Believer that hath begun ought to goe forward to perfect his duty to God, all theſe I grant according to the ſenſe of your three Arguments, and that the laying on of hands ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. is not meant of Church Officers, nor of the ſick, I grant, but that it is not meat to ſuffer Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I doe not grant; but I ſhall ſay more to that when I come to anſwer to the things we differ about in your laſt Chapter; and then I ſhall ſee whether your ſtrong piece of armour will keep the body of your diſcourſe from being wounded or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:168156:9"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>The next thing you allege for the proof of your Poſition is your Conſequences: that the Church of the Jews and the Church of the Romans, had ſubjected to laying on of hands; for the Church of the Jews, your conſequence is driven from <hi>Acts</hi> 2.42. From theſe tearmes, They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Apoſtles doctrine, which tearm Doctrine, you compare with that in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1. and argue thus. That if they continue in the Apoſtles doctrine, then they were in the Apoſtles doctrine: but (ſay you) the former is true: therefore the latter will follow. Secondly, ſay you, if they were in ſubjection to the Apoſtles doctrine, and laying on of hands was a part of the Apoſtles doctrine, then they were in ſubjection to that: but they were in ſubjection to the Apoſtles doctrine, and laying on hands was a part of the Apoſtles doctrine. <hi>Ergo.</hi> But ſay you, this Concluſion ſome will deny, becauſe we find breaking of bread, and fellowſhip mentioned all in one verſe <hi>Act.</hi> 2. which you confeſs were doctrins of Chriſt, preached and practiſed in thoſe times, and yet you ſay, they were never part of that you call the Beginning doctrin, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. And as for the Church of the Romans you conclude, they were under laying on of hands, becauſe in <hi>Romans</hi> 6. the Apoſtle tells them how they had obeyed from the heart the form of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrin, which you apply to <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1. and tell us, that theſe ſix principles are the ſum of all the doctrines of the Goſpell: for (ſay you) all theſe ſeveral duties commanded in the Goſpel, may be reduced to ſome of thoſe principles; as you ſay, you could ſhew if time would permit, and ſo you conclude to ſay no more for the proof of that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, that the tearm Doctrine, in the ſecond of <hi>Acts,</hi> is the ſame with that in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1. the grounds you alleage, do not prove; and as for the <hi>Minor</hi> part of your two Arguments, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. ſpake one word
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168156:9"/>about laying on of hands, it is denied, and you brought nothing but your own words to prove it: and in your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the objection againſt your Concluſion, you confeſs that breaking of Bread, and Fellowſhip, were doctrines of Chriſt, preached and practiſed in thoſe times; and yet you ſay, they were never part of that you call, the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doctrin, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. And yet in your next page, you tell us, that thoſe ſix principles are the ſum of all the doctrins of the Goſpell, and that all thoſe ſeveral duties commanded in the Goſpell, may be reduced to ſome of thoſe principles; but how in one page you can ſhut out breaking of Bread, and Fellowſhip, from being any part of that you call the Beginning doctrine, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6. and yet in your next page, join them all together, I know not; but at the leaſt you either forget your ſelf, or els your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment altered as you were writing; but ſeeing theſe laſt grounds alleged by you are but conſequences, the life of which (if they have any in them) muſt be fetched from <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. And becauſe all you have ſaid in this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; according to the ſenſe of your third Argument, ſerves but to prove, that thoſe that have not laying on of hands as unbaptized perſons, have it as baptized perſons, which may be true in the caſe of ſufferings, or when hands are laid on, in order to the Receiving of the Holy Ghoſt: for becauſe in theſe two Caſes of ſubjection to laying on of hands, the parties ſubjecting, do it not as unbaptized, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they do it as Baptized; ſo though all you have hitherto ſpoken is hardly worth anſwering, yet I thought good to ſpeak a little to it; that your ſelf and others might ſee the weakneſs &amp; unſoundneſs of it, and ſo much by way of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to what is paſt, <hi>viz.</hi> Your 1. and 2. Chapter, And as for your third Chapter wherein you ſpeak of the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: if ever you can prove your practice it ſelf to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted from command, our difference about the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168156:10"/>will be eaſily ended, till which time, I ſhall ſay no more to your third Chapter. In your fourth Chapter, you lay down theſe four particulars to be the ends wherefore laying on of hands is to be adminiſtred upon Baptized be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, that they may be put into a further capacitie, to go on to perfection; Secondly, that they may compleat their ſubjection, as in relation unto the principles of the foundation; And thirdly, that they may compleat the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of their ſubjection; And fourthly, that they may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by demonſtrate their love to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>As to your firſt end you lay down, if your kinde of laying on of hands could be proved by command, as it never hath been yet proved, yet this your end is denied, <hi>viz.</hi> That laying on of hands doth put any man into a further capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to go on to perſection, for theſe Reaſons: becauſe the Text you bring to prove it, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. doth not ſpeak, nor hold forth any ſuch ſenſe: as I deſire the Reader will well conſider of; but I ſhall ſay more in order to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planing of this Text, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6. in my anſwer to your laſt chapter. A ſecond Reaſon why laying on of hands doth not put believers into a further capacitie to go on to perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is, becauſe not actions, but the indowments of nature, together with the teachings, and commanding part of the Scriptures, do fully capaciat men, not only to begin, but alſo to go on to ſuch perfection, as God requires of any of the ſons of men, as appears, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. where it appears the noble man, namely Chriſt, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his ſervants, and delivered unto them his goods, and as in <hi>Luk</hi> 19. <hi>ver.</hi> 13. ſaid unto them, <hi>Occupy till I come;</hi> to one he gave five tallents, to another two, to another one, to every one according to his ſeveral abilities, or as every one was capable to improve; the ſecond and the firſt, to their capabilitie did improve their talents; but the third,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168156:10"/>though he was as able to improve one, as the other were to improve five or two, yet did not one action well-pleaſing to his Maſter; From whence, it is clear, that actions do not capaciate men for work, becauſe that this man was in a capacity, and yet had done nothing well-pleaſing to his Maſter; from all which its clear, that the indowments of nature, together with the teachings of God, do fully capaciate men, both to begin, and alſo to finiſh their dutie; and as for the other three ends, if the means you uſe in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the attaining of them, were commanded by God, <hi>viz.</hi> Laying on of hands, ſo as you practiſe it, I ſhould not deny them: but ſeeing laying on of hands, ſo as you pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it, was never commanded by God, you do no more compleat your ſubjection, nor the order of it, nor demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate love to Jeſus Chriſt, than they do who ſprinkle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants: for they think, they do God as good ſervice, in ſprinkling Infants, as you do by laying on of your hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your account, that is, without reſpect had to healing, or receiving that great gift of the Spirit, or ordaining to office: ſo that ſeeing your kinde of laying on of hands is no where commanded by God, you do but confound your ſubjection and the order of it, and demonſtrate want of love to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>In the next place you tell us, that thoſe who hold, that hands were laid on in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. for the receiving of the extraordinarie gifts of the Spirit, have nothing but ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition for their ground: and all the Reaſon you can ſhew againſt it, is Firſt, becauſe the tearm extraordinarie is not found in the Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. Secondly, becauſe as you ſay, an ordinarie thing is as ſoon beheld as an extraordinarie. Thirdly, becauſe as you ſay, <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was a carnall wicked man, and for ought you know might be as much miſtaken in his ſeeing the Holy Ghoſt given through lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of the Apoſtles hands, as he was in offering money
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168156:11"/>to buy the power. Fourthly, you endeavour to prove, that the Apoſtles had no ſuch power, as to give the Holy Ghoſt, from <hi>Acts</hi> the 4.9, 10. And fiftly, your endeavouring to diſtinguiſh between the, end of a thing, and the effects of a thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, though the tearm extraordinarie be not in the Text, yet you know, it notes out unto us, ſome great thing, unuſual, or not common to all; and though by way of anſwer to an objection which ſaith, the gift was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie, becauſe <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſaw it, you ſay, <hi>Simons</hi> ſeeing of it doth not prove it extraordinarie; becauſe an ordinarie thing is as ſoon beheld as one extraordinarie; but I ſhall deſire the Reader ſeriouſly to conſider, whether ordinary reception, of the Spirit which are onely internal, and do not demonſtrate themſelves by ſuch external opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as thoſe we call extraordinarie do; for the greater the gift is, the greater externall operations do appear; and ſo this great gift outwardly demonſtrating it ſelf, <hi>Simon</hi> ſaw it, for the common or ordinarie gifts of the Spirit, are like, if not the ſame, with that hidden <hi>Manna,</hi> and white ſtone, wherein is the new name written, which no man knowes but he that receives it, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.17. Therefore <hi>Simon</hi> could not ſee the ordinarie, but the extraordinarie gift of the Spirit. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it was an extraordinarie gift: and this gift, the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. will further appear to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie, if we compare Scripture with Scripture: for when we read of the Holy Ghoſt being given, it notes out more than an ordinatie gift, for we read of five times in the <hi>Acts,</hi> that the Holy Ghoſt was given, and in three of them it is expreſſed how they ſpake with tongues, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. the 10. and the 19. and in the 57. page of your Book, you confeſs, that in the 4. of the <hi>Acts</hi> where the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt was given, it was an extraordinarie gift, yet there is nothing expreſſed that they ſpake with tongues, or that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168156:11"/>it was extraordinarie; and though in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, that it was extraordinarie by ſpeaking with tongues, yet comparing this gift, <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. with the other four places, where the Holy Ghoſt was given in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie way, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. the 4. the 10. and the 19. And obſerving the ſame tearmes, by way of falling upon them, and thoſe notable operations which <hi>Simon</hi> ſaw, and took notice of, which drew his deſire to buy the power of giving the Holy Ghoſt, through laying on of hands, it will appear it was extraordinarie; and whereas you ſay, <hi>Simon</hi> was a carnal wicked man, and for ought you know might be as much miſtaken in his ſeeing the Holy Ghoſt given through laying on of the Apoſtles hands, as he was in offering them money to buy the power; it appeares, that he was not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in what he ſaw; becauſe the Holy Ghoſt takes it for granted, in theſe words, Now when <hi>Simon</hi> ſaw, that through laying on of the Apoſtles hands, the Holy Ghoſt was given, he offered them money, ſaying, Give me alſo this power, that on whom ſoever I lay hands, he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Holy Ghoſt: as if he had ſaid, that glorious and wonderfull power, which the Apoſtles had, as a gift from God, through laying on of hands, inſtrumentally to give the Holy Ghoſt, drew <hi>Simons</hi> deſire to have it himſelf; And whereas you ſay <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had no ſuch power, as through laying on of hands to give the Holy Ghoſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Peter</hi> declared to the men of <hi>Iſrael Acts</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. that by the Name of Jeſus did he that was cured ſtand whole before them, from whence you infer, that as <hi>Peter</hi> had not the gift of healing, ſo not the power of giving the Holy Ghoſt, yet <hi>Acts</hi> 4. and the 10. doth not prove, that <hi>Peter</hi> wanted power upon either acount: for if you look into <hi>Acts</hi> the 3. the 4, 5, 6. where <hi>Peter</hi> bad the lame man look on them; it is ſaid, he gave heed to them, expecting to receive ſomething of them, but <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto him, ſilver
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168156:12"/>and gold have I none, but ſuch as I have give I thee, <hi>In the Name of Jeſus Chriſt of Nazareth, ſtand up and walk;</hi> from whence it is clear, though <hi>Peter</hi> had no ſuch power of his own procuring, yet he had it by vertue of gift from God, as appeares from theſe words, Such as I have give I thee; and if you look into <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. you ſhall not only ſee how that the Apoſtles had ſuch a power, but alſo how they came by it; for ſpeaking of Chriſt, the Text ſaith, He called his Diſciples, and gave them power over unclean ſpirits, to caſt them out, and to heal all manner of ſickneſs, and all manner of diſeaſes: from all which it is clear, that the twelve Apoſtles, of which <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were two, had a power given them from God, to do miracles, and heal all manner of diſeaſes; and again, if <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had not received from God a power inſtrumentally to give the Holy Ghoſt, through laying on of hands, <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould have reproved <hi>Simon</hi> for two faults; Firſt, for thinking that they had ſuch a power, as they had not; Secondly, for thinking that power which God gives freely, might have been purchaſed with money: but you may ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>v.</hi> 20, 22. when <hi>Peter</hi> comes to reprove <hi>Simon,</hi> he reproves him only for one ſingle ſin, committed by way of thought, ſaying unto him, Thy money periſh with thee, becauſe thou haſt thought that the gift of God might be purchaſed with money, and <hi>verſe</hi> 22. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith to him, Repent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of this thy wickedneſs, and pray God, if perhaps the thought of thine heart may be forgiven thee: from whence it is cleer, that <hi>Simon</hi> did not ſin, in thinking <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had a power, as inſtruments, through laying on of hands to give the Holy Ghoſt; becauſe <hi>Peter</hi> did not reprove him for two miſtakes in the plural, but onely for one fault in the ſingular: in theſe words, Pray God, if perhaps the thought, not the thoughts, of thine heart may be forgiven thee: ſo that it is clear, the Apoſtles had a power inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168156:12"/>through laying on of hands, to give the Holy Ghoſt; And <hi>Simon</hi> was not miſtaken in what he ſaw, nor in what he thought, as touching their power; but this one thing was his ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> in thinking that that ſpiritual power which God then gave to thoſe his ſervants <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> might be purchaſed with corruptible ſilver or gold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben:</speaker>
               <p>Again ſay you Antagoniſt, Suppoſe it ſhould be granted by way of ſuppoſition, that theſe in receiving the Holy Ghoſt, did receive the extraordinary gifts of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, yet this is nothing to prove what they ſay, <hi>viz.</hi> That laying on of hands upon Baptized believers, was to this end, that they might receive the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit; and why? here is a great miſtake in laying down this to be one end; for in this here is no difference put between the End of a thing, and the Effect of a thing: men common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propoſe their end before hand, that is before they do their work, but the effect followes the work done: as for inſtance, the end wherefore the Husband-man plowes and ſowes, is that he may have his ground fruitfull; the effect it may ſo fall out, it will be barren again: the end wherefore ſuch a one builds a houſe is, that he may dwell in it; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect perhaps may ſo fall out, that it may be blown down of winds, and ſo become uſeleſs. Again, I ſhall give you another inſtance: two Miniſters of Chriſt, they go to ſuch a place to preach, their end is to convert ſouls, the effect is, they are claped up in priſon, and perſecuted, as ſome have been: and ſo you conclude, the gift of the Holy Ghoſt was not the end, but the effect of their laying on of hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, you ſay, ſuppoſe it were granted, that theſe in receiving the Holy Ghoſt, did receive the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary giſts of the Spirit, yet it will not prove, that they laid on hands to that end, becauſe as you ſay, we greatly miſtake in not putting a difference between the end and the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168156:13"/>effect of a thing: but I muſt tell you, I think that you have not dealt fairly: for at firſt you ſeem to us, as if you would diſtinguiſh between the end and effect of one and the ſame thing, and yet in your three inſtances the ends &amp; effects you ſpeak of, relate to ſeveral cauſes; For though it is true, the end wherfore the husbandman plowes and ſowes, is that he may have his ground fruitfull; yet though barrenneſs fall out, it is no effect of his plowing and ſowing; for the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and proper effect of plowing and ſowing, is to make the ground fruitfull, and barrenneſs is the effect of ſome croſs cauſe, as either blaſting, or overmuch drought, or ſome ſuch like. And ſecondly, it is true, the end wherefore a man builds a houſe, is that he may dwell in it, but if the effect be blowing down, yet this effect ariſeth not from the mans building of it, but from another croſs cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> great winds. And thirdly, if any of Chriſts Miniſters go to any place to preach, it is true, their end is to convert ſouls, but if they be clapt up in priſon, it is no effect of their preaching, though you ſeem to affirm it is, for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bears no ſuch bitter fruit as impriſonment, but their impriſonment is the fruit or effect of a contrary croſs cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the malicious proceedings of wicked men the Devills inſtruments: ſo that it is clear, you ſaid, we were mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in not diſtinguiſhing between the end of a thing, and effect of a thing; it is clear, your ſelf is miſtaken; becauſe the end and effect you ſpeak of, belong not to one and the ſame thing, but receive their beings from direct contrary cauſes: now that which a man deſires, or aimes at, or layes down as the end wherefore he uſeth meanes, is the ſame which through the meanes inſtrumentally is effected or brought to paſs; again, the Husbandmans deſire, or aim, or end, is through the uſe of meanes to enjoy a plentifull har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt; and if no croſs cauſe prevent, the thing effected, or brought to paſs, is a plentifull harveſt: ſo that it is clear, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168156:13"/>end, aim, or deſire, and the thing effected, is one and the ſame in ſubſtance; and all you have ſaid makes nothing againſt their opinion, who hold, that the great and large gift, the Holy Ghoſt, was the end wherefore <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> laid on their hands <hi>Acts</hi> 8. for in verſe 15. it is ſaid, they prayed for it, which argues, it was their own end and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have it, and ſo much by way of Anſwer to your fourth Chapter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>As to your fift Chapter, the ſubſtance of what you ſay here, is included in your former grounds, and is alſo anſwered in my foregoing matter, and therefore for brevities ſake, I ſhall take notice onely of ſuch things as I have not already anſwered: and in the firſt place, though you confeſs in your Book, page the 51. that in former times the Holy Ghoſt did attend the practice of laying on of hands, and in page the 53. do grant, that thoſe twelve men <hi>Acts</hi> the 19. did receive the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit; and yet you deny, that the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit are eſſential to it, from <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt tell your Antagoniſt, that laying on of hands will ſtand as firm and unmoveable, in theſe our dayes, without any ſuch extraordinary appearances of the Spirit, as formerly, for theſe Reaſons; firſt, becauſe the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit were to confirm the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel, and it being confirmed, there needs no ſuch extraordinary gifts to that end, and ſo you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, they confirmed laying on of hands, as well as the reſt of Chriſts doctrine, putting no difference between actions and doctrine; a ſecond reaſon why you conclude, that miracles, and the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, are not eſſential to laying on of hands, is, becauſe theſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary appearances of God, are not eſſential to any other Ordinances of God, as you inſtance in Preaching and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Acts</hi> 10, and <hi>Acts</hi> 4.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168156:14"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer, although you grant the extraordinary gifts of the Spirit did attend laying on of hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. yet you deny they were eſſential to it: becauſe you ſay. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. no extraordinary gift followed laying on of hands; but in this you have laid a ground for your own miſtakes, by comparing that ſort of ſubjection to laying on of hands, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. to that ſort in <hi>Acts</hi> 19. where they ſubjected in order to the receiving of the Holy Ghoſt, but in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. I ſhall hereafter make it appear, that they ſubjected in order to the filling up the meaſure of the ſufferings of Chriſt, therefore you muſt not think to make us believe, that the extraordinary gift of the Holy Ghoſt is not eſſential to that kind of laying on of hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. and the 19. becauſe it is not eſſential to that contrary kind of ſubjection to laying on of hands, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not eſſential to preaching, and ſome kind of prayer, for indeed preaching, and ſome kind of prayer were never appointed to be inſtrumental for giving the extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary gift, the Holy Ghoſt, but the proper effect of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is to convey the ordinary gifts of the Spirit, as inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and many other comfortable Receptions, ſo that though the extraordinary gift of the Holy Ghoſt be not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to preaching, it never being appointed as the means through which this gift ſhould be given, yet they may be and are eſſential to that kind of laying on of hands, through which they were given, and never failed, as <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. &amp; <hi>Acts</hi> the 19. The Scripture ſpeaking but of thoſe two times that this ſort of laying of hands was uſed; ſo that I wonder that you ſhould ſay as you do, <hi>viz.</hi> That we may no more ty up the reception of the extraordinary gift, the Holy Ghoſt, to laying on of hands, then we may to preaching the Word; becauſe, as you ſay, the extraordinary gift, the Holy Ghoſt, did attend preaching, as well as laying on hands; And this you ſay, though you may ſee <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. &amp; the 10. this gift,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168156:14"/>the Holy Ghoſt, was given through laying on of hands, but though we find <hi>Acts</hi> the 19. this gift was given when they were at preaching, yet never through preaching. And whereas you ſay, the extraordinary gift, the Holy Ghoſt, did confirm laying on of hands <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. as well as it did Preaching <hi>Acts</hi> the 10. I anſwer, it did confirm laying on of hands <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. ſo as to beſpeak the lawfulneſs of the uſe of that means being uſed in order to the ſame end, <hi>viz.</hi> receiving the Holy Ghoſt: And ſo did miraculous healing confirm or beſpeak the lawfull uſe of laying on of hands, to that end, <hi>viz.</hi> to heal.</p>
               <p>But again, it is true, and you confeſs it in the 6. page of your Book, that the non-being of the gift of healing in the Church doth beſpeak the uſeleſneſs of laying on of hands to that end, <hi>viz.</hi> to heal.</p>
               <p>And ſo on the other hand, I ſhall affirm, that the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of power in the Church inſtrumentally, through lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands, to give the Holy Ghoſt, doth beſpeak the uſeleſneſs of laying on of hands to that end: And ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that though God hath the ſame power now, as he had then, yet, if in his wiſedom he ſees it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> convenient to will the giving of the ſame gifts now, as he did then, his power doth not accompliſh it: for his power doth act ſuitable to his will; for, if in his will, he doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin a thing, then by his power he doth not effect it; and ſo he divides to every one ſeverally as he will, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. And when in his wiſdom he ſees it convenient to give thoſe glorious gifts into his Church, as he did formerly, he can again begin the diſpenſation of them without the uſe of outward inſtruments, as he did at the firſt to the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
               <p>And as to the things you call effects of your laying on of hands, <hi>viz.</hi> as you ſay, a moſt ſweet and precrous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and a delightfull fellowſhip in the Goſpell; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168156:15"/>more of the manifeſtation of Gods Spirit to their ſouls. Thirdly, to be further ſtrengthened in Gods way; for your firſt effects, <hi>viz.</hi> A moſt ſweet and precious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, you inſtance in thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> the 2.41, 42, 46. in which place there is not one word mentioned, that ever they had hands laid on them, and therefore though they had a ſweet Communion, yet it did not ariſe from laying on of hands; and as for theſe three particulars which you call ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, you might more properly have laid them down, as three more ends, which though they are propounded before hand yet for ſuch, are the ſame with effects, and then, though you had not attained to them, yet at the leaſt we ſhould have thought you ſhould have deſired them; but now you have laid them down as effects, what ever you may ſay, I with many other can from ſad experience teſtify, that in inſteed of a ſweet and reall Communion in the Church of Chriſt; your kinde of laying on of hands hath effected nothing but an unſavory outſide Communion, and hath furniſhed our meetings with many vain jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. And Secondly, inſteed of more of the manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods Spirit, I ſee nothing but unſound arguments effected by your kinde of laying on of hands. And thirdly, inſteed of being further ſtrengthened in Gods way, there are many can witneſs with me from ſad experience, how that your kind of laying on of hands hath weakned the Church of Chriſt, and fruſtrated many proceedings which tended for the good of the Church of Chriſt, as in the relation to the choice and ordination of Officers; and alſo much hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the increaſe of the Church: but how you will anſwer theſe things you know not. I confeſs you have cited many excellent Scriptures in theſe two laſt Chapters, if you had not wrong applied them; but having wrong applied them, they are of the more dangerous conſequence: therefore let all that fear God, take heed; and ſo much as to your fift chapter.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168156:15"/>
               <p>In your laſt chapter, you ſay, that ſome do queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this is any command of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> laying on of hands upon Baptized Believers: but by the way I muſt tell you, that this is like many other of your raſh and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper aſſertions, for laying on of hands upon Baptized Believers, is an action, not a command, for command re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives its being from God, but actions receive their being from the creature, enabled thereunto by the Creatour: but I ſhall take your meaning, namely, that you mean that there is a command from Jeſus Chriſt, which injoins Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Believers to ſuffer hands to be laid upon them; for proof of which you ſay, doctrines are equivalent to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and how <hi>Robert Everat</hi> at a diſpute at <hi>Tharpe,</hi> did grant, that doctrine and command are tearms equivalent, and then you ſay, that in the ſecond epiſtle of <hi>John</hi> verſe the 6. compared with the 9. we ſhall find, that the ſame thing which is called command in the one place, is called doctrine of Chriſt in the other; but that is but your own words; but becauſe I love plain dealing, ſuppoſe it ſhould be granted, that doctrins are equivalent to commands, yet it will not follow, that their proper quality is one and the ſame; for the proper quality of doctrine is to teach, and the proper quality of command is to bind or oblige the creature to the doing the thing taught; yet their equivalency doth appear, in that they as branches ſpring both from one root, and like ſtreams flow both from one fountain, and thirdly, the one hath as much authoritie to teach, as the other hath to command: yet as in relation to their proper ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or quality they are two diſtinct things, as I ſaid before: But if it were ſo that doctrine and command could be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be both one in all reſpects, yet they that have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doctrine nor command for their practice, are never the neerer, as you have not.</p>
               <p>But becauſe your practice, <hi>viz.</hi> laying on of hands upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168156:16"/>Baptized Believers, as a diſtinct thing, for which as you ſay, Chriſt hath given order by it ſelf, without reſpect had to the attaining that great gift, the Holy Ghoſt, which we call extraordinary, or without reſpect had to inſtating into office, or healing infirmities, or to the ſuffering perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſay, becauſe this your practice will appear to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a truth or an error, from the right underſtanding of that Text, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. Therefore I ſhall deſire to take that counſell which <hi>Paul</hi> gave to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. Namely, rightly to divide the Word of Truth: and now, firſt, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew the weakneſs and unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe things you conclude, or lay down from <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1, 2. and then declare what I underſtand from it; only this, I think we agree in, <hi>viz.</hi> That the tearm Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in this place ſignifies only beginning things, and not at all chief things: becauſe then this abſurdity would follow, <hi>viz.</hi> That then the <hi>Hebrews</hi> muſt leave the chief things, and go on to practiſe thoſe of leſs concernment; and as for the tearm foundation which doth as it were open the ſenſe of the former tearm Principles, it alſo notes out only the beginning of things; and now what you ſay from the Text, and ſo now I ſhall take notice of your laying down Laying on of hands, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. to be a part of the foundation of the Church: for you running a parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the 80. page of your Book, you cite the 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.12. to prove that <hi>David</hi> had command from God for every thing done in the material houſe or Temple; where ſay you, Was there a command for the ſtones to be laid upon the ſoundation in the firſt houſe? and then ſay you, Is there not a command for lively ſtones to be laid upon the foundation in the latter houſe? which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire may be well conſidered, and ſo I hope it ſhall. Anſwer, Firſt, conſider what you are here proving, a command: for it is laying on of hands, or ſubjection to laying on of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168156:16"/>hands ſpoken of in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. which laying on, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to laying on of hands, you do here cleerly note out unto us to be a part of that foundation, upon which the lively ſtones are to be laid now in this latter houſe; and for my further ſatisfaction of this, to be your opinion, I have not my ground only from what you ſay in print, but alſo upon a certain time at <hi>Earlſhilton,</hi> as you were a preaching to a great audience, about laying on of hands, you were ſhowing the weakneſs of that opinion of thoſe who held, that the laying on of hands <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. was meant of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, in denial of which you ſaid, that it could not be that; becauſe there cannot be officers in a City before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the City be laid: And when you had ended your ſpeech, I deſired you to tell me what you meant by the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and what by the foundation; you told me, that by the City, you meant the Church; and by the foundation, you meant theſe ſix particulars which you called principles, to be the foundation of the City, which is the Church; the ſame doth <hi>Mr. Fiſher</hi> affirm in his long argument, and two or three times more in his book; but now I deſire you and all other whom it may concern, to conſider what you have made the foundation of the Church of, <hi>viz.</hi> of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures actions, works or duties; for repentance is the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures action, work or duty, and ſo is faith <hi>John</hi> 6.29. and ſo is Baptiſm, and ſo is ſubjection to laying on of hands; and alſo Faith, to the Reſurrection and eternal Judgment; Now theſe being all actions, works or duties, of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (being imperfect in the beſt of Saints) are too ſandy to make a foundation for the Church; But if it could have been proved (as it never can) that the actions of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are the foundations of the Church, yet you would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your ſelves confuſed builders, in bringing that which you call a part of the Churches foundation, and lay it upon the top of the houſe after it is built; for I have heard you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168156:17"/>grant in your exerciſe at <hi>Markfield,</hi> that Faith and Baptiſm do render a Church rightly conſtituted, and if ſo, then that you call a part of the foundation is laid upon the houſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is built, and not onely ſo, but you lay it upon every ſingle ſtone belonging to this houſe, if they will ſuffer it, but wiſe builders do not uſe to do ſo; therefore in this alſo, you render your ſelves confuſed builders: but when you ſee that the actions of the creature will prove too ſandy a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the Church of Chriſt to be built upon, then you ſay you mean Chriſt in his doctrine, or to ſpeak plainly, that this doctrine it ſelf is the foundation of the Church, as in page the 29. of your Book, line 16, 17.</p>
               <p>But for anſwer to this, though it is true, the doctrines of Chriſt are uſefull and very excellent in their places, and for thoſe ends and uſes God hath appointed them, yet they cannot be the foundation of the Church, for theſe reaſons: Firſt, becauſe of the unſuitability of the matter; for the reſt of the matter of the Church doth conſiſt of lively ſtones, believing-men, and women, <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. And what muſt the reſt of the matter, <hi>viz.</hi> the foundation, be made of words? that cannot be, becauſe tis inconſiſtent with the reſt of the matter of the houſe.</p>
               <p>A ſecond reaſon why doctrines cannot be the foundation of the Church, is, becauſe of the ſhortneſs of their duration, in compariſon of the duration of the Church, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare thus: for when men have done ſinning, that doctrine which teacheth repentance ſhall ceaſe; and when we injoy that by ſenſe, which we have now but by Faith, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which teacheth us to believe, ſhall ceaſe; and when we have wholly mortified the old man, and are perfectly riſen to newneſs of life, that doctrine which teacheth Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſhall ceaſe; and when the Tyrant or oppreſſor is taken off, that doctrine which teacheth ſufferings from the hands of wicked men ſhall ceaſe; and when the Reſurrection and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168156:17"/>eternal Judgment are paſt, theſe doctrins which teach as in relation to them ſhall ceaſe: now if theſe doctrins ſhould be the foundation of the Church, when the Church comes in its moſt triumphant ſtate, <hi>viz.</hi> after the Reſurrection, it will have loſt its foundation: <hi>Ergo,</hi> not for that uſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, doctrins cannot be the foundation of the Church, becauſe God hath appointed them for another uſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to fit the matter for the building; Secondly, for to inform the builder how to lay the fitted matter into the building; And thirdly, how to order it well, when it is built; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it is compared to a Hammer, and to an Axe, and to a Line: ſo that it cannot be the foundation, but rather the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument wherewithall the builder fits his matter for the building, as Chriſt told his diſciples, <hi>John</hi> the 15.3. ſaith he, <hi>You are clean through the Word which I have ſpoken to you,</hi> where you ſee the Word fits the matter for the houſe, by clenſing of it; and in the 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17. It is ſaid, that the Scripture ſerves to perfect the man of God, and throughly to furniſh him to every good work; and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the matter, <hi>viz.</hi> The lively ſtones, fit for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters uſe: now the doctrine being the chief inſtrument which fits the matter for the houſe, no wiſe builder will lay his tooles under the houſe for the foundation of it: ſo that you may ſee from theſe three reaſons, that though do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines be excellent in their place, and for that end and uſe God hath appointed them, yet they cannot be the foundation of the Church: But if we look into 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us what is the foundation, in theſe words, <hi>Other foundation can no man lay, than that which is, Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Now, I deſire you, and the Impartial Reader, to conſider, whether it is his perſon or his doctrine, which all along in Scripture is called <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for that which is properly called <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the foundation of the Church; now if we take him for the foundation, which
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168156:18"/>is indeed the foundation, and none other can be laid, then the Church ſhall never want a foundation: as in <hi>John</hi> the 8.35. Chriſt ſaith of himſelf, <hi>The ſon abides in the houſe for ever:</hi> and therefore it ſtall never be unprovided.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſtion.</hi> But ſome may ſay, upon what account is Chriſt the foundation of the Church, as in his Perſon?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Chriſt is the foundation of the Church in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, upon this account, in that he is the firſt born of many Brethren, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. Firſt in the Fathers love, the firſt fruits of them that ſlept; and firſt upon every account; and ſo the firſt lively ſtone in this ſpiritual building, which muſt needs be the beginning of this building, and the beginning of this building is the foundation of this buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and ſo you ſee Chriſt is the foundation or beginning of the Church, and none other can be laid; and he having three places in this ſpiritual houſe, is alſo ſaid to be the chief Corner-ſtone, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. And thirdly, he is alſo the head of this houſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22.</p>
               <p>And ſo the wiſdom and goodneſs of God doth moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly appear, in making choice of ſuch a holy, perfect, durable and lovely lively ſtone, to be the foundation, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſtone, and head of this houſe. Therfore take heed of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Chriſt out of any of his places, and ſetting other things in his ſtead, for it is not a ſleight matter to put any of the things of God out of their proper places. Now we have ſeen that theſe particulers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. cannot be the foundation of the Church, neither in reſpect of actions, nor doctrine; let us examin what thoſe foundations, or principles are, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. The Authour exhorts the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to leave the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples or foundation, which tearm foundation, explains what is meant by the tearm principles, <hi>viz.</hi> the beginning, for foundation is a beginning, leaving the beginning, may ſome ſay of what? why? ſaith the Author, according to <hi>Mr. Tindals</hi> tranſlation, which you confeſs in your Book, page
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168156:18"/>the 74. is a plain tranſlation, and I alſo in that place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1, 2. Judge it to be the trueſt tranſlation that ever I ſaw: for faith the Author, leaving the beginning of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, of Faith, of Baptiſm, of Doctrine, of Laying on of hands, of Reſurrection, and eternal Judgment; So that it is clear, that the Author doth not apply the tearm foundation, or beginning, to the whole worke of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor the whole work of Faith, nor to the whole work of any of the other five, but only the firſt ſteps or degrees of repentance, are here called foundation, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and ſo the firſt ſteps are degrees of all the reſt: but if the tearm foundation or beginning, ſhould here have been applyed to the whole work of Repentance, and ſo of all the reſt, we muſt leave out the tearm <hi>of,</hi> and read it thus, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaving the foundation Repentance, Faith, Baptiſm, Doctrine, Laying on of hands, Reſurrection, and Eternal Judgment.</p>
               <p>And if the whole ſum of theſe ſhould be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and the foundation ſo to be left, as to go on to perfection in degrees of higher doctrine and practice, and if that be true, which you ſay in the 23. page of your Book, that thoſe ſix you call principles, are the ſum of all the doctrine of the Goſpell; then men lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as the exhortation counſells, thoſe things which you ſay are the ſum of all the doctrine of the Goſpell, men are left uncapable of perfecting any thing in relation to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or practice of a higher nature, for there can be none beyond the number all; But on the other hand, if we apply the tearm foundation or beginning, not to the whole work, but only to the firſt ſteps or degrees of repentance, and ſo of all the reſt, then men are left in a full capacity to leave the firſt degrees, and to go on to perfection, as to what is behind: the teacher having laid the firſt ſteps or degrees of teaching, may paſs from that, and go on by degrees, till he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168156:19"/>hath perfected teaching, and ſo the practitioner alſo may leave the firſt ſteps or degrees of repentance, faith, &amp; all the reſt, and go on to perfection in the remaining degrees of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, with all the reſt; we cannot begin and perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, faith, nor any of the reſt, all at once.</p>
               <p>For the Teacher in his firſt Sermon, may either expreſly or implicitly, in the vertue of them, lay the firſt degrees of all ſorts of teaching: as for inſtance, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. There is a ſhort ſermon in theſe words; He that believes and is Baptized ſhall be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Here may be ſaid to be implicitly the firſt degrees of all ſorts of teaching; but if the Teacher will perfect what he hath begun, he muſt by going on from one degree to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, expreſly ſhow, that to faith muſt be joyned faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in all particulers, and to Baptiſm muſt be joyned mortification of ſin, and reſurrection to newneſs of life, or els, neither Faith nor Baptiſm will avail for ſalvation; and ſo the Practitioner may lay the firſt degrees of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, both internal and external, at his firſt converſion, but till he have done ſinning, he cannot perfect the work of repentance: and ſecondly, though he may begin the work of faith, at his firſt converſion, yet till he be perfect in knowledge he cannot perfect faith: for knowledge muſt precede faith.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, though he may begin Baptiſm: yet he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to have perfected it untill he hath quite morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſin, and is wholly riſen to newneſs of life.</p>
               <p>And fourthly, though a Saint may begin his duty of ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, at his firſt converſion, ye he muſt daily take up the croſs of Chriſt, and follow him towards perfection in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.10.</p>
               <p>And fiftly, though a ſaint may begin faith to the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and eternal Judgement, at his firſt converſion, yet he cannot attain to the perfect knowledge of, and faith in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168156:19"/>them, untill he be a very ſtrong Chriſtian indeed: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares from <hi>Paul,</hi> who was at that time paſt a babe in Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10, 11. where he deſires to know Chriſt, and the power of his Reſurrection, and the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, being made conformable to his deaty, if by any meanes I may attain to the reſurrection of the dead, not as though I had already attained, or, were already perfect, but I follow after it, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>So that you may ſee, that the attaining to perfection as to theſe particulars; is a task ſufficient for the time of a Chriſtian mans life: ſo you ſee what is here meant by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the principles or foundation, and what it is to go unto perfection, <hi>viz.</hi> To leave the beginning part of teaching and practice, and go on by degrees towards perfection in both.</p>
               <p>In the next place, let us come to examin what ſort or kind of ſubjection to laying on of hands, is meant in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. that we minde the parties ſpoken to, as ſubjectors to, and not Adminiſtrators of laying on of hands, I think it is granted on both ſides: and that this ſubjection to laying on of hands, was not in relation to their receiving offices; nor in relation to their receiving healing, is out of diſpute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you and I; For, it is not poſſible, that all the Church of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſhould receive Offices; neither is it likely, they were all ſick, ſo as to have hands laid on them, to heal them; neither did they ſubject to that end, as to receive the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary gift of the Holy Ghoſt; neither was it ſuch a ſubjection to hands, as you plead for, <hi>viz.</hi> That Saints ſhould have hands laid on them, meerly as conſidered Baptized believers, without reſpect had to office, or healing, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the great gift the Holy Ghoſt; or ſuffering perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution from the hands of wicked men; becauſe that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to hands, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. relates to a doctrine of Chriſt, but this which you plead for, and uſe without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:168156:20"/>had to the forementioned things, was never taught by Chriſt nor his Apoſtles: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is no kin to that, in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. but if you ſay, it was taught in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. I anſwer, there was not one word expreſſed by way of teaching, in relation to any ſorts of ſubjection to laying on of hands, as I have formerly ſhewed; moreover, that laying on of hands <hi>Acts.</hi> 8. was uſed to this end inſtrumentally, to give the Holy Ghoſt, as I have already proved at large.</p>
               <p>And as your kinde of laying on, or ſubjection to laying on of hands, was never taught by Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles; neither did they ever give command for it: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it cannot be that ſpoken of <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. So ſeeing it cannot be meant of any of the former: Therefore it muſt needs be meant of ſubjection to ſuffering, from the perſecuting hands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, for theſe following reaſons: Firſt, becauſe upon that account Chriſt taught it, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.12. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.38. <hi>Marke</hi> 8.34. and upon this account <hi>Paul</hi> alſo taught it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.12. and ſecondly, upon this account, Chriſt commanded it, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. <hi>If any man will be my Diſciple, let him take up his Croſs daily, and follow me;</hi> and ſo <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 1.29. <hi>It is given as in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thirdly, becauſe upon this account, Chriſt, our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Leader, was under it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.67. <hi>then did they ſpit in his face, and buffetted him, and others ſmote him with the palmes of their hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And fourthly, it muſt needs be it, becauſe of the Greek tearm <hi>Kiron,</hi> which relates to him which inflicts puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Saints, which renders him in his ſo doing evill, wicked, or far worſe, as the tearm <hi>Kiron</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies.</p>
               <p>And fiftly, ſubjection to ſuffer from the perſecuting hands of wicked men, muſt needs be intended <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. becauſe there is no other ſort of ſubjection to laying on of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168156:20"/>ſteps or degrees of, and to go on by degrees, as to the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the ſame work of ſubjection.</p>
               <p>Theſe reaſons grounds alleged by me, to prove that that ſort of ſubjection tohands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. is meant of the Saints ſuffering perſecution from the hands of wicked men, being well conſidered, I am ſure will prove the truth of it, againſt all the reaſons that can be brought to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
               <p>As touching ſubjecting as Officers, all the Saints are not in a capacity, nor in relation to healing, and as for that ſort of ſubjection done in order to the receiving the Holy Ghoſt, it is begun and ended all at once, as is clear from <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. for we never read, that they never ſubjected more upon that account, and the ſame you affirm in your own Book, and though all the Saints are not in a capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to leave the firſt ſteps or degrees, and go on to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in point of ſubjection, as to any of theſe three ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> in relation to Office, healing, and receiving the Holy Ghoſt, yet all the Saints are in a full capacity to leave the firſt degrees of ſufferings, from the hands of wicked Men, and as occaſion is offered go on to perfection, as their Captain and leader hath done <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. ſo that you ſee, or at leaſt wiſe may ſee, that it is clear that, that ſubjection to laying on of hands, ſpoken of <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. muſt needs be meant of ſuffering perſecution from the hands of wicked Men. Firſt, becauſe upon that account Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles taught it. Secondly, becauſe upon that account Chriſt and his Apoſtles gave command for it. Thirdly, becauſe upon that account Chriſt and his Apoſtles were underſtood. Fourthly, becauſe the Greek tearm <hi>Kiron Heb.</hi> 6.2. notes out unto us, that they who perſecute Gods people, are evill and wicked men; and the laſt reaſon is not the leaſt, it is becauſe there is no other ſort or kind of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168156:21"/>laying on of hands, which all the Saints are in a capacity to leave the foundation or beginning part of, and go to perfection to higher degrees of the ſame ſubjection; but it may be ſome may queſtion, how all the Saints may be ſaid to ſuffer by laying on of hands from wicked Men: ſeeing wicked Men by way of ſtripes do not lay their hands upon all the Saints.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Though it is true, it is not likely all the Saints ſhould ſuffer ſtripes from the material hands of wicked Men; yet if the Saints ſuffer impriſonment, or death, or any other hurt by means of him, who it may be never touched them with his own material hands, they may be ſaid to ſuffer from or under their hands, as in <hi>Jer.</hi> 26.14. where you may ſee in the 8th. <hi>ver.</hi> that <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and taken Priſoner, and in the 14. <hi>ver.</hi> he ſaid unto them, <hi>As for me, I am in your hands, do with me as it ſeemeth good unto you;</hi> here you ſee, that <hi>Jeremiah</hi> tels them, that he was in their hands, which term hands implies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that he was their Priſoner and under their cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, not that he could be properly ſaid to be in one ſingle hand, he ſpeaking to many Men: And ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. it is ſaid, that <hi>Herod</hi> the King ſtretched forth hands to vex certain of the Church, and having killed <hi>James</hi> with the Sword, and he ſaw that pleaſed the <hi>Iews,</hi> he proceeded further and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned <hi>Peter</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>From whence it is clear, that the Saints ſuffering from the power or wicked Plots of Men may be ſaid to ſuffer from or under their hands, though their material hands never touch them; for no Man will conclude that <hi>Herod</hi> ſtretching out the hands of his Body could vex the Church, or that he killed <hi>Iames,</hi> or impriſoned <hi>Peter</hi> with his own material hands; but on the contrary, being ſet on work through malice, by his power commanded his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168156:21"/>to do it; ſo you ſee the Saints may properly be ſaid to ſuffer under the hands of wicked Men, though they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſmite them with their material hands; ſo you ſee this queſtion is fully anſwered.</p>
               <p>In the next place, I ſhall come to ſhew the weakneſs and unſoundneſs of thoſe reaſons you lay down againſt this ſubjection to laying on of hands <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. to be meant of the ſame ſuffering perſecution from the hands of wicked Men.</p>
               <p>Firſt you ſay it is very abſurd, or ſtrange, to think that Chriſtian Men ſhould be perſecuted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In theſe words you diſcover either Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or elſe unfaithfulneſs; for that I plead for was not perſecuting, but to ſuffer perſecution, therefore you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover unfaithfulneſs, in that you ſeem, as if this were the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of ſome, when I am perſwaded you never heard any Man ſay it was his opinion, that Chriſtian Men ſhould be perſecutors. Secondly, you diſcover Ignorance, becauſe you mind thoſe parties ſpoken to <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. as Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators, whereas it is clear they were ſubjectors to, and not Adminiſtrators of laying on of hands in no ſenſe at all, ſo that theſe words of yours, make nothing againſt the Saints ſubjection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. to be meant of ſuffering perſecution under the hands of wicked Men.</p>
               <p>In the next place you ſay it cannot be ſo meant, becauſe this laying on of hands <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. particularly belongs to Chriſtian Men in point of ſubjection. Let us leave the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in this ſay you, Saints are active, but in ſufferings they are Paſſive, therefore ſay you, it cannot be meant ſuch a ſort of laying on of hands.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, here you grant truth, which in your former words you ſeemed to deny it; in this reaſon you ſay it appertains to Chriſtian Men in point of ſubjection; but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168156:22"/>when as you ſay it cannot be meant of ſufferings, becauſe they are exhorted to leave the Doctrine, and you ſay in this Saints are active, but in ſufferings they are Paſſive, though in leaving the firſt degrees, &amp; going on higher in ſom ſenſe they may be ſaid to be Active, yet Saints that have hands laid on them, upon what account ſoever it is, they are Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, for they ſuffer others to do it, and therfore not Active, ſo that this confuſed reaſon makes nothing againſt its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meant of ſuffering perſecution.</p>
               <p>Your next reaſon, why it cannot be meant of ſuch a kind of ſubjection to laying on of hands; becauſe the Saints of God are often to ſuffer perſecution for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, but as to the laying on of hands declared <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. they are but once to undergo, as is evident from the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Scripture, let us go forth to perfection, and now no more lay the foundation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In that you ſay the Saints are often to ſuffer perſecution for the Goſpel, it is true, and that ſerves to prove that which I affirm, <hi>viz.</hi> That Saints are to leave the beginning part of ſufferings, and go on to perfection in them.</p>
               <p>But whereas you ſay that Saints are but once to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go that kind of laying on of hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. you plainly declare what you underſtand by leaving the beginning, &amp; going on to perfection, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Saints ſhould leave ſubjection to that ſort or kind of laying on of hands, which you conceive to be firſt practized, and then go on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in relation to the number of thoſe ſorts or kinds of laying on of hands which remain.</p>
               <p>But that your opinion cannot be true upon this account, I thus prove, becauſe though it is true, that all the Saints may ſubject to on ſort of laying on of hands, <hi>viz.</hi> that of ſuffering perſecution, its not poſſible all the Saints by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:168156:22"/>way of ſubjection, ſhould perfect the number of ſorts or kinds of laying on of hands, becauſe all the Saints ſhall never ſubject as Officers, nor as ſick parties, nor by way of receiving the extraordinary gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing this, therefore your opinion that Men ſhould leave the beginning, or firſt ſort, and go on to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as to the number of ſorts that remain of laying on of hands, cannot be true, becauſe it is not poſſible all the Saints ſhould do it; and as it cannot be true upon your account to leave the firſt, and to go on to perfection as to the number of ſorts of laying on of hands, on the other hand it both may and muſt be true, from <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. that Saints are to leave the firſt ſteps or degrees of ſubjection to one ſingle laying on of hands, and go on to perfection in the remaining degrees of the ſame ſubjection, to one and the ſame ſort of laying on of hands, which will hold true in the caſe of ſuffering perſecution, and not in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I have already proved.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <p>His third reaſon againſt ſubjection to laying on of hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. to be meant of ſuffering perſecution, is, becauſe the laying on of hands, we here contend for it is a principle of Chriſts Doctrine, whereas contrary ways for wicked to perſecute the Saints is a principle of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Doctrine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <p>Anſwer. See how confuſed your own reaſons ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you in your opinion; for in the beginning of your foregoing reaſon, you confefs that the laying on of hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. peculiarly belongs to Chriſtian Men in point of ſubjection, and yet in this your third reaſon, have tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Caſe quite contrary, in that you ſeem to note out unto us, that thoſe parties inſtructed by the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2. were layers on, and not ſubjectors to laying on of hands.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:168156:23"/>
               <p>But if you agree with me, that the parties inſtructed by the Doctrine of Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. were ſubjectors to, and not layers on of hands, as that you muſt do, except you can prove all the Church of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to be Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
               <p>So that Chriſt teaching the Saints to ſuffer for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, though it be from or under the hands of wicked Men, is no point of the Devils Doctrine, but of his own, and you have deceived your ſelf, becauſe in this your third reaſons you ſeem to apply this point of Chriſt, teaching to layers on, and not to ſubject to laying on of hands.</p>
               <p>So that you may clearly ſee the weakneſs, and unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all theſe reaſons you have rendred againſt my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion from, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. <hi>viz.</hi> that ſubjection to laying on of hands there held forth, is meant of the Saints ſuffering perſecution from the hands of wicked Men for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels ſake; But again Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> denyes that it is meant of the Saints ſuffering perſecution from the hands of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Men; becauſe ſaith he, it is included in the Doctrine of Baptiſms, and therefore would be confuſion and a tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology to expreſs it over again under the tearm Laying on of hands.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Becauſe I would have no objection unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, I ſhall ſay ſomething to this ſubtle reaſon, and firſt it is improper to apply or call Baptiſm, or any of the other five by the name of Doctrine, as will appear, becauſe there muſt be a clear diſtinction put between Doctrine or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching matter; onely which comes from God, and the thing taught, which on the Creatures part is to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: For Repentance, Faith, Baptiſm ſufferings for the Goſpel, Faith in the Reſurrection and general Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being the Creatures actions, performed either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally or externally, being capaciated thereto by vertue
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:168156:23"/>of the doctrinal or teaching matter, which comes from God, muſt needs be improperly called Doctrine, and therefore Maſter <hi>Tindal</hi> in his Tranſlation, ſets down the tearm Doctrine; which our common Tranſlations apply to be Baptiſm, as a diſtinct thing by it ſelf, between Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and laying on of hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. and ſo partly Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and laying on of hands, which you ſo often tell us follows next in order the one to the other, ſo that you may ſee how improper it is to call Baptiſm, or any other action of the Creature by the name of Doctrine, ſeeing it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs onely to the Creators teaching, and not to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures action, In the next place Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> reading it Baptiſms <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. in the Plural number is not like to be true. 1. Becauſe moſt of the Greek Copies, if not all, and many of our common Tranſlations, and Maſter <hi>Tindals,</hi> which is one of the antients, plain, and ſoundeſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, we find, read it Baptiſm in the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Again to read Baptiſm, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. in the Plural, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be right, becauſe it cannot be proved that all the Church of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> to whom this was ſpoken, were either Baptized with ſufferings, or with the Spirit, that they were not Baptized within or under ſufferings is clear, becauſe the Baptiſm of ſufferings conſiſts of an over-flowing, or an over-whelming meaſure of ſufferings, which many, if not all times takes in death it ſelf, as for inſtance the two Sons of <hi>Zebedec,</hi> and alſo Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.50. where ſaith he, But I have a Baptiſm to be Baptized with, and how am I pained till it be accompliſhed.</p>
            <p>From whence its clear, that every degree of ſufferings is not the Baptiſm inſuffering; becauſe Chriſt had ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red very many things before he ſpake theſe words, and yet he ſaith, he had his payning or ſtreightning Baptiſm
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:168156:24"/>to be Baptized with ſtill, ſo that every degree of ſufferings is not the Baptiſm in ſufferings.</p>
            <p>But as the tearm Baptiſm ſignifies in all caſes, ſo it muſt be an over-flowing, or an over-whelming meaſure, which renders a Man Baptized with ſufferings, with which meaſure of ſufferings it cannot be proved, that the Church of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were all Baptized; for though they had ſuffered great afflictions, yet it was no other than what Chriſt had ſuffered before he begun his Baptiſm of ſufferings, <hi>viz.</hi> to be made a mocking ſtock.</p>
            <p>And as it is in the caſe of being Baptized in ſufferings, ſo it is in the caſe of being Baptized in or with the Spirit; for every degree of receiving the Spirit, will not render a Man Baptized with the Spirit, as is clear from <hi>Acts</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. where in the 4. <hi>ver.</hi> Chriſt commanded his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples not to depart from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but wait for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Father, which ſaith he ye have heard of me.</p>
            <p>And then in the 5. <hi>ver.</hi> ſaith, <hi>John truly Baptizea with water; but ye ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptized not many days hence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we may obſerve, that the Diſciples here ſpoken of too, were not yet Baptized with the Spirit; for if they had, it need not be promiſed to be diſpenſed upon them a few dayes after.</p>
            <p>And though they had not the Baptiſm of the Spirit when theſe words were ſpoken to them, yet they received ſo much of the Spirit, as that they were true believers, true converts born of the Spirit, which render Men capable of Salvation able to caſt our Devils, and to heal all manner of ſickneſs and diſeaſes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.1. and yet not Baptized with the Spirit.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee every degree of receiving the Spirit, is not the Baptiſm of the Spirit; but it muſt be ſuch an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing meaſure of the Spirit, whereby a Man is able by
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:168156:24"/>an immediate power to ſpeak all Languages, as appears from <hi>Acts</hi> the 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 2, 3, 4. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> the 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4.5. Where <hi>Acts</hi> the 1. <hi>v.</hi> 5. it was promiſed to be given to them a few days after, and in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. being ſome days after, you ſee it was given; and alſo it was, <hi>viz.</hi> a power to ſpeak with tongues, which all beleivers in thoſe days were not able to do, as is clear from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29, 30.</p>
            <p>So that we may ſee from theſe grounds which I have laid down, how at that time not, any of thoſe ſpoken to, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.2. were Baptized in ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Neither is it likely they could all ſpeak with tongues, and ſo not be Baptized with the Spirit; ſo that Maſter <hi>Fiſher</hi> reaſons againſt that ſubject to laying on of hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. to be meant in the caſe of ſuffering perſecution for the Goſpels ſake, grounded upon that text, reading Baptiſm in the Plural is quite taken of, and he that well conſiders what I have ſpoken in this Book, may ſee the weakneſs and unſufficiency of all the grounds he hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaged by his laying on of hands.</p>
            <p>And alſo here is diſcovered the miſtakes of thoſe who put no difference between, to be Born of the Spirit, and to be Baptized with the Spirit; which fits Men to Preach the Goſpel to all Nations; which was the ſpecial end of that gift, as appears from <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. compared with <hi>Acts</hi> the 1. <hi>ver.</hi> the 5. Chap. 2. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>Thus with as much moderation and tenderneſs as I could, and not let you ſuffer, I have anſwered to the ſubſtance in what is contained in your Book. I might have been lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; but that I think I ſhall be forced again to put Pen to Paper, as in relation to this thing, I intreat you and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who it may concern, not to ſlight or condemn any
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:168156:25"/>thing that is here ſpoken of, till you have often read and well conſidered it, and if God ſhall have uſed me as an Inſtrument to ſpeak convincingly to the conſciences of any, I deſire that they will give God the Glory, and ſtrive to learn that heard leſſon of Self-denyal.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:168156:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
